每一代人都会重新定义宇宙的边界
Each generation reinvents space as the cosmic frontier
在加加林、薛帕德那个时代
In the age of Gagarin and Shepard
试飞员总会向摄像机笑一笑来证明他们不是假人
test pilots grinned into the TV cameras to prove that they were made from the right stuff
而到了2018年，造火箭却变成了身家亿万的投资商为所欲为之为所欲为的平台
and in 2018, orbital space is becoming the playground for billionaire entrepreneurs
让他们儿时的梦想变为现实
turning their childhood dreams into reality
大家印象里，NASA的管理者都是一群老气横秋的人
In this picture the administrators at NASA are the dull old guys in the
慢慢榨干政府给的钱
background dishing out most of the government money
来签各种项目，每每问及他们都说“咕咕咕在做啦”
to established aerospace contractors, always seem to be under delivering and be behind schedule
虽然有数十亿的资金，大家也都知道
Despite the billions of dollars in funding, so the story goes
但NASA让我们太失望了，没造成行星际飞船，月球基地也没信
NASA has let us down by failing to build interplanetary spaceships or lunar bases
更甭想什么星际殖民防止地球再闹个物种灭绝之类的幺蛾子
and no off world colonies have been established to protect us against accidental extinction
所以NASA真的如此效率低下吗？
But is it true that NASA works too slowly
如果是真的，那其他国家的航天企业咋还没打败NASA呢？
And if so why haven't they been beaten to the punch already?
那些私家飞船和私家空间站都哪去了？
Where are the privately funded spaceships or orbital stations?
太空叉老总马一龙显然认为他的公司能打败NASA从而第一个送人类去火星
SpaceX's Elon Musk apparently believes his company can beat NASA to a manned landing of Mars
但他也不是第一个有如此野心的人
but he's not the first to have such grand ambitions
仔细了解下NASA和美国几家私企的关系
A closer look at the relationship between NASA and private enterprise in America
你会发现不知两家公司在比赛谁先去那颗红色星球
reveals that there is much more than a two horse race to the Red Planet
尽管航天的历史进程看上去像迈了几个大跨步
Although space history sometimes feels like a series of giant leaps
但屏幕能看到的部分不少都是他们为达到宣传目的而特意挑选的
the small steps that appear on our screens are largely selected to be good PR and marketing
而不是真正想反映当前的航天科技水平
rather than a reflection of the current aerospace technology
NASA至今已经六十年了
NASA is 60 years old this year
但其具体资金如何，还要看每个四年内的总统政府到底能给你多少
but its annual budget depends on what it can deliver within each 4-year cycle of American politics
即便是大家都资瓷连任的总统也是如此
even if a president expects two terms in office
对于NASA超过八年才能见到成效的项目
Any NASA project that takes longer than eight years to get results
要么让总统名垂青史，要么直接被毙了
will either heap glory on his or her political opponents or face cancellation
肯尼迪总统从宣布要送人去月球到实现用了七年
President John F Kennedy's commitment to send astronauts to the moon took seven years to achieve
即便当时NASA的经费（换算过来）是今天的八倍
even with funding at eight times what it is today
航天飞机也叫太空运输系统（STS）
The Space Shuttle also known as the Space Transportation System (STS)
也是早在1968、69年，阿波罗任务刚载人飞行的时候就开始构思了
was in planning when the first manned Apollo missions flew in 1968 and 69
七十年代早期，公众开始不愿意在航天上砸太多钱，航天飞机计划面临取消
By the early 1970s, public support for expensive projects was fading and the Space Shuttle faced cancellation
为了留住项目，NASA重新设计了可复用轨道器，使其不但能载平民，还可适配军方任务
To save the project, NASA redesigned the reusable orbiter to be able to fly both civilian and airforce missions
结果就是航天飞机极其复杂又昂贵
The result was that the shuttle became hugely complicated cumbersome and expensive
1981年首飞的时候，里根总统刚上任
When the first missions began in 1981 when Ronald Reagan entered office
发射任务就已经严重拖后了
the launch schedule was much slower than planned
说好的一周一飞，变成了一年四飞
The promised weekly flights became an average of just four missions per year
虽然从今天来看还算是个不错的转变
But by today's standards that seems like a decent turnaround
NASA的航天飞机需要许多子系统的精准配合，它们被分配给几个不同的承包商
NASA's Shuttle required the precise coordination of advanced subsystems, built by different contractors
这当中一些著名的航天与防务部门贡献最大
The largest contributions came from the famous names in Aerospace and Defense
轨道器是在加州帕姆代尔的北美罗克韦尔公司制造
The orbiter was built in Palmdale California by North American Rockwell
发动机由洛克达因公司研发，外挂燃料箱来自马丁·玛丽埃塔公司
The engines were developed by Aerojet Rocketdyne, the external tank was built by Martin Marietta
命运多舛的固推来自莫顿聚硫橡胶公司
and the ill-fated solid rocket boosters with a responsibility of Morton Thiokol
如果最开始航天飞机项目单独签给一家公司，那可能就和其他公司没关系了
If the Space Shuttle had been built by any one corporation it would have probably put them out of business
但通过NASA的航天飞机项目，美国政府建立起了
But through NASA, the US government was able to fund an
在当时不太可能出现的、依靠当时全球最强经济体的技术联合体
unlikely combination of technologies using the power of the world's largest economy
这样说来，航天飞机项目还算成功
In those terms the Shuttle program was a success
其作为一个先进的发射系统，服役了整整三十年
building, flying and servicing a pioneering launch system over three decades
但不看好航天飞机的人认为，航天飞机的复杂设计让每次飞行都如履薄冰
But to its critics, the compromised design made every mission a disaster waiting to happen
步入21世纪，航天飞机已到迟暮之年，美国急需新的发射系统
At the beginning of the 21st century the shuttle was shown its age and a new launch vehicle was desperately needed
但研发进度大家都能想到，简直史无前例地慢
But the development was, as you've guessed it, progressing even more slowly than ever
2003年2月，哥伦比亚号航天飞机再入大气时解体，七人遇难
In February 2003, the orbiter Columbia was destroyed on re-entry costing the lives of its seven crew members
事故调查期间美国的航天项目搁置两年
America's space program was grounded for two years whilst a thorough investigation was carried out
同时，加州的一小队航天工程师正在微调他们新的可复用航天飞机
Meanwhile in California a small team of aerospace engineers were fine-tuning their own reusable space plane
可能搞一个世界级大新闻
which were about to make world news
伯特·鲁坦的公司的缩尺复合体决定争夺Ansari X奖项
Burt Rutan's company Scaled Composites was competing for the Ansari X Prize
一千万美元奖励给第一个能在两周内发射两次高度超过100千米的飞船的非政府组织
worth $10 million to the first non-government organization
to launch a spacecraft above 100km altitude twice within 2 weeks
2004年9月29日和10月4日
On September 29th and October the 4th 2004
鲁坦的太空船一号在白骑士号的携带下先后达到了102千米与115千米的高空
Rutan's Spaceship One launched from White Knight to 102km and then a 115km
打破了40年前X-15飞机创下的纪录
flying higher than a record set by the X-15 40 years earlier
也让太空船一号赢得了Ansari X奖
and enabling Spaceship One to win the Ansari X PRIZE
英国企业家理查德·布兰森马上掏钱，想让太空船一号变成能进太空的商业坐骑
British entrepreneur Sir Richard Branson immediately set out to turn Spaceship One into a commercial ride into space
并宣布在莫哈维沙漠建一个太空船发射、降落场
announcing plans for a spaceport in Mojave Desert
布兰森宣布他的新公司名字叫维珍银河
Branson initially said that his new company Virgin Galactic
将在2007年进行亚轨道飞行，之后推到2009年
would begin suborbital flights in 2007, but soon revised the date back to 2009
船票卖的挺快，二十五万美元一张
Seats began selling fast at a cool $250,000 each
布兰森还弄来不少私人投资
Branson also managed to secure vast sums in private funding
包括来自阿布扎比主权财富基金的三亿美元投资
including almost $300 million from Abu Dhabi Sovereign Wealth Fund
但在幕后，太空船二号发动机升级的研发则非常缓慢
However behind the scenes development was progressing slowly on the engine for the updated Spaceship Two
太空船二号将采用基于过氧化物的火箭发动机，由内华达山脉公司制造
a high test based peroxide rocket motor built by the aerospace company Sierra Nevada
在2014年10月，人们加深了对维珍银河公司的怀疑
Skepticism about Virgins ambitious schedule intensified in October 2014
太空船二号——企业号试飞发生事故
when disaster struck a test flight of the VSS enterprise
事故详情见av21807258 《空中浩劫S18E06：2014年维珍银河太空船2号解体事件》
当飞船跨音速的时候，太空船二号的羽翼机构过早部署
Whilst passing the speed of sound, the feather mechanism on a Spaceship Two was deployed too early
导致太空船二号在五万英尺高度解体，试飞员之一麦克遇难
and the VSS Enterprise broke up at an altitude of 50,000 feet, and one of the pilots Michael Ellsbury was killed
这次事故是灾难性的，尤其对于布兰森的太空旅行构想来说
The accident was a catastrophe, not least for Branson's attempt to market Spaceship Two as the future of space tourism
尽管设计大改，维珍银河公司还是把工作重心转向了设计一些适中的项目
Despite major changes in the design, Virgin Galactic has shifted focus to more modest projects
比如在改装后的747下放一个小型发射系统
such as its small static launch system using a modified Boeing 747
太空新时代正在到来
The era of new space was underway
但其中的危险却贯穿整个载人航天的历史
but for dangers were as real as they had been for the whole history of manned space flight
2011年7月21日，亚特兰蒂斯号航天飞机在佛州肯尼迪航天中心最后一次着陆
On 21st of July 2011, the Space Shuttle Atlantis touched down for the last time at the Kennedy Space Center in Florida
从此美国没法送人进太空了
leaving America without a manned space vehicle
这一尴尬局面让NASA不得不求助俄罗斯
This embarrassing gap in capability would leave NASA dependent upon the Russians
来送美国的宇航员去国际空间站，而俄罗斯也为此获利不少
for getting its astronauts to and from the ISS and the Russians were making the most out of the situation
2008年航天飞机还在的时候，俄罗斯向NASA的开价是每座位2160万美元
In 2008 when the shuttle was still around, Roscosmos charged NASA $21.6 million per seat
但航天飞机退役后，船票就一路飙升
but after the Shuttle was retired that price went up dramatically
用了快五十年的联盟号飞船的船票
The cost of a seat on the Russian Soyuz, a 50-year-old expendable vehicle
到了2018年涨到了每座位8100万美元
but had outlived all of its competitors in 2018 is now $81 million
NASA的下一代发射系统也是融合了两种退役的系统
NASA's next-generation Launch System was also shaping up to be a combination of two retired systems
顶端飞船是类似阿波罗构型的，下面级则是类似航天飞机的橙罐加两个固推
An Apollo type command module atop of a Shuttle style orange fuel tank boosted by two solid fuel Rockets
被取消的星座计划中的战神火箭改了改
Adapted from the Ares rocket canceled from the Constellation Program
变成了新的“太空发射系统”（SLS）
the new rocket went by the no frills name of a Space Launch System or SLS
高111米，比土星五号高一点点
At 111m, the evolved SLS will be just a bit taller than the Saturn V
但性能强多了，近地轨道运力130吨
but more powerful and able to lift a 130 tons to low Earth orbit
拉倒吧早就咕到2020年后了
构型1将在不早于2019年的时间首飞
The SLS will launch no sooner than 2019 beginning with block 1
将把猎户座载人模块在内的70吨载荷送进近地轨道
which will begin with a capacity of 70 tons payload including the manned Orion module to low Earth orbit
波音负责造芯级
Boeing is commissioned to build the core stage
下面四台RS-25发动机由洛克达因公司升级，每台提供418,000磅（190吨）推力
powered by four RS-25 engines, upgraded by Aerojet Rocketdyne to provide 418,000 pounds of thrust
比其上次用于航天飞机的时候推力增加了5%
a 5% increase in power from when they last flew on the Space Shuttle
新的固推也在研制中，和航天飞机一样，交给轨道ATK公司来做
New solid rocket boosters under development at the same company that built them for the Shuttle Orbital ATK
用于航天飞机上的四段固推被升级成五段
have been upgraded from four segments in the shuttle boosters to a new five segment design
SLS的上面级也是从现有技术升级而来的
The SLS upper stage were also upgrade from existing technology
YouTuber口误 是“Delta IV” 不是“Delta V”
用的是ULA的Delta IV火箭的二级作为临时过渡用的低温推进系统
Taking United Launch Alliance's Delta IV second stage and adapting it to become the interim cryogenic propulsion stage
使用单台RL-10发动机送载荷入轨
using a single RL-10 engine to lift the payload into orbit
RL-10发动机首次服役是在1962年
The RL-10 engine first saw service in 1962
（可以说是氢氧机里的天顶星科技）
是美国最古老的氢氧火箭发动机
making it America's oldest liquid hydrogen rocket engine
按计划，当2022年SLS构型1B发射时
When the block 1b launches in 2022, according to current plans
它将使用更大的探险号上面级
it will be upgraded to the larger Exploration Upper Stage
运力增加至近地轨道105吨
increasing the payload capacity 105 tons to low Earth orbit
使用四台RL-10C-3发动机，届时，RL-10系列发动机就真的是“花甲之年”了
using four RL-10C-3 engines, and by then, the RL-10 will be a sixty-year-old design
对于去月球和火星的比赛，乌龟和兔子谁赢还不好说
In the race to the moon and mars, the tortoise may eventually beat the hare
紧跟NASA步伐，杰夫·贝索斯为蓝色起源选了座右铭“Gradatim Ferociter”
Taking NASA's approach, Jeff Bezos chose the motto for Blue Origin: "Gradatim Ferociter"
意思是“一步一步前进,摆脱一切牵绊”
which means step by step ferociously
他们公司的徽章长这样，俩王八从佛州和加州起飞飞向宇宙
To illustrate, the company's coat of arms bears a pair of giant tortoises on either side of America
climbing upwards from Florida and California towards other worlds
贝索斯的公司拿着NASA的钱也在一步一步前进
Bezos's company has benefited from NASA investing in slow incremental development
尤其是在一些可靠、成熟技术专业知识的培养上
not least in the way this has nurtured expertise in reliable, proven technologies
一些航天与防务部门的大公司的工程师与技术人员
Engineers and technicians from the big Defense and Aerospace companies
都想去太空叉和蓝源工作
have been persuaded to move to SpaceX or Blue Origin
不但工资高，还有参与新的太空竞赛的魅力感
with lucrative salaries and the glamorous image of the new space movement
不管这些工程师、科学家安身何处，NASA的赞助肯定从来不会缺席
Wherever these engineers and scientists are based, NASA awards funding in much the same way as he always has
和往常一样，支持竞争对手之间的提议
by backing proposals from the strongest competitors
而别看马一龙送假人进太空这事比贝索斯那傻屌座右铭更出名
And although Elon Musk is more famous for putting crash-test dummies into orbit than writing mottos
太空叉的可回收火箭也在不停迭代进步
his company SpaceX has also steadily iterated their fly back boosters
今年5月，可多次复用的构型5也成功发射了
towards the rapidly reusable block 5 due to launch for the first time in may 2018
有了亿万富翁的资助，使得太空叉这样的公司真的敢随便炸火箭
With a billionaire entrepreneur part funding the project, spectacular rapid unscheduled disassemblies
而像洛马、波音这样的公司就不敢这样乱尝试
have been more exceptabtle from a SpaceX brand than they would have been for ones like Lockheed Martin or Boeing
他们在可靠性上的声誉可经不起几次试飞里的爆炸
whose reputation for reliability depends upon avoiding the bad press of an exploding test flight
这是NASA这样的公共企业与私企之间新的合作关系带来的真正益处
This is the real benefit that emerges from a new partnership of public and private space organizations
NASA通过支持一些投机的技术，可快可慢
NASA can be both fast and slow, supporting speculative technologies
详情见av14923456
比如资助太空叉这样的公司，能把自己家火箭失败剪辑成NG集锦
through companies like SpaceX, whose PR machine can turn a string of failures into a viral blooper reel
接下来是狗尾续貂、跑题时间
当私人太空旅行实现的时候，一定会引起全世界的关注
When private space tourism takes off the world will be watching
我们也只能希望飞船的可靠性有所提升
and we can only hope that the spacecraft will be a reliable step forward
而不是真·送你上天
rather than a dangerous detour on the way to a wider access to orbit
在一次大张旗鼓的首飞后，最有可能的是
After the first well-publicized flights, the likelihood is
太空旅行的需求量暴涨，使得太空行业突然蓬勃发展
that there will be more demand for out-of-this-world transport than any one company can meet
大叔你这说的什么跟什么 跟标题有毛关系？
而其中更安全的公司，顾客也可能更青睐
A reputation for safety will win more customers than the boasts of those who cross the line first